just before the Titanic sank to the
bottom of the ocean the ship sent out a
distress signal containing its exact
location the coordinates sent out by the
Titanic were extremely useful the nearby
ship arms Carpathia quickly headed
towards them and in fact all survivors
of the Titanic were rescued by this ship
and if it was easy to find the lifeboats
it seems like it would be easy to find
the wreck but this turned out to be
wrong and locating the ship became a
puzzle that would take Decades of
technological advancements to solve and
spurt a race between several explorers
all competing to be the
first this is how the Titanic was
found with the last known location of
the Titanic already recorded the most
immediate question after it sank wasn't
focused on finding the wreckage but
rather how to raise it from the ocean
floor nearly 2 and 1/2 miles below to
surface technology just wasn't there in
1912 for divers to reach even a fraction
of such deaths and absurd ideas such as
using Dynamite to dislodge the bodies
from the wreck were quickly scrapped it
would take more than 40 years in two
world wars that brought with them
technological advancements such as
submarines and sonar for the first
serious expedition to head back out to
the Titanic's last known location in
1953 risten Beasley the founder of a
salvage company from England decided to
try his hand at finding the
impossible visible here are the
coordinates from the distress call the
Titanic mate before it sank sent out at
10:35 p.m. New York time but even with
the coordinates in hand the search
radius has to be quite a bit larger the
distress call was made 2 hours before
the entire ship slipped beneath the
water time in which the Titanic could
have drifted and the currents could have
pushed the ship even further while it
was sinking the ocean is vast and trying
to find one single a point on the ocean
floor in complete darkness is nearly
impossible wisdon Beasley began by
dropping Dynamite over the reported
location of the Titanic wreckage these
explosives would create an echo that
using Sonar could be plotted to create a
bottom profile which Beasley hoped would
reveal the ship basically a very
imprecise early version of sonar mapping
in fact too imprecise to yield any
results as Beasley found no
luck 20 more years would pass after his
attempt when Robert Ballard a marine
geologist wanted to make
history in 1977 the Woods Hole
oceanographic institution had developed
new survey equipment for mapping out the
ocean floor Ballard was tasked with
testing this new state-of-the-art tech
but personally his motivation lied with
using this equipment for finding the
Titanic in the middle of the ship was a
hole that would allow a long pipe to be
extended into the water just above the
ocean floor attached to the end of this
pipe Ballard rigged a pot that contains
sonar and cameras with the hope that it
would be able to detect the Titanic's
wreckage once the ship passed above it
the expedition began with some early
tests when suddenly disaster struck the
drill pipe broke sending thousands of
feet of pipe and the pot containing the
expensive equipment crashing to the
ocean floor ending the search before it
could even
begin heartbroken and embarrassed
Ballard had to return to the institution
without the expensive equipment he was
set out to test and without any hint on
the
Titanic more years would pass and even
during an age where the technology had
finally Advanced enough it should
theoretically be possible to find the
Titanic having the resources to
undertake such an expedition was another
matter entirely every trip had the
potential to cost hundreds of thousands
of dollars and not many were willing to
part with so much money for what could
be a fruitless
sech that is until Jack Grim entered the
scene Grim was an eccentric oil tycoon
based out of Texas and he was no
stranger to trying to find the
impossible he had previously tried to
find Noah's Ark and he had also financed
expeditions to find the loches monster
Bigfoot and even an attempt to prove the
hollow Earth theory by trying to find a
large hole in the North Pole now Grim
was determined to solve the mystery of
the Titanic
even though Grim had the money he lacked
the other piece of the puzzle the
technology and knowledge he knew he
would need a capable team with the
expertise to work the equipment that
would be required to accomplish this he
donated
$300,000 to the geological Observatory
of the Columbia University in New York
in exchange for the equipment and crew
he needed for to search he would be
joined by renowned scientist Dr William
Ryan and Dr Fred SP an unlikely alliance
between two renowned scientists and a
conspiracy theory-driven oil tycoon
perhaps exactly what's needed to find
the ship it seemed everything was lined
up for this expedition to be a success
but Grimm believed one thing was still
missing always a believer in spectacle
Grim surprised the scientists by
bringing a monkey named Titan on board
grim whim claimed that this monkey was
trained to point at a map and is able to
figure out where the Titanic should be
located Dr Ryan and Dr spe were shocked
not used to Scientific Pursuits being
joined with what they considered a
performance
act the scientists threatened to leave
the Expedition and told Grim directly
that it is either them or the monkey and
to their surprise Jack Grim actually
chose the
monkey in the end cooler heads prevailed
and Grim was finally persuaded to leave
Titan behind and the Expedition could
finally begin the crew headed to the
coordinates from the Titanic's distress
call and they would lower a side looking
sonar attached to a cable into the ocean
which would be towed along the ocean
floor this type of sonar sends out
acoustic pinks to each side this way
there is a small area beneath the probe
without any data but on the sides large
areas of the ocean floor can quickly be
mapped and unusual shapes and bumps are
spotted once such a shape has been found
an onboard magnetometer would be used to
detect if that shape is metal
essentially if it is man-made or just a
natural feature of the seabed finally
transponders were dropped in the ocean
that would keep track of the sonar
itself so any areas of Interest could be
precisely marked with
coordinates but even after searching the
entire area around the ship's
coordinates the crew found nothing and
increasingly the scientists started to
doubt the accuracy of the initial
coordinates even though the Titanic gave
its last known location here the
survivors that escaped in lifeboats were
actually picked up around here much
farther east than they should have been
even accounting for ocean drift knowing
this the scientists theorized that the
coordinates the Titanic gave were
actually wrong as the first officer did
not account for a time change as they
were traveling and the only reason the
Carpathia was still able to rescue
people was because the actual recite was
somewhere within the path towards the
false
coordinates this opens the search area
quite significantly and they now believe
the Titanic had a high probability of
being somewhere in this
1,500 M
rectangle with the old coordinates ruled
out it was time to Once Again Begin
searching the crew used a process
commonly referred to as mowing the lawn
Towing the sonar in overlapping lines
each pass they would marked anything
that stood out from the sonar's readings
but there was an issue the magnetom
meter which was supposed to let them
know if any of these abnormal shapes
were metal was broken and to make
matters worse bad weather rolled in
threatening the entire Expedition itself
determined to carry out the mission they
still carried on and continued marking
every abnormal area of Interest they
came across and each time they found a
new one Grim's excitement grew
continuing until the last area was
marked making 14 in total Grim was
convinced that one of these areas had to
be the Titanic but he wouldn't get the
chance to prove it time had run out the
charter for the equipment in the ship
they were using was about to expire and
they needed to head home not ready to
give up over the course of the next year
the scientists and Grim prepared to set
back out once again this time using a
more advanced sonar than the one they
had used
previously one by one each area was
looked at in more detail and one by one
they were ruled out as natural features
on the very final day ready to give up
they decided as a lasted effort to try
to use digital film the camera would be
fixed on a sled and dragged above the
ocean floor after passing the route the
camera was brought up to review the
footage and while watching a new strange
shape began to
appear looking closer it started to look
more and more like a propeller
Grim was immediately convinced that they
had done it they had found a piece of
the
Titanic unfortunately though the time
had run out and before they could
investigate further they were once again
forced to head home feeling that victory
was just Within Reach Grim was ready to
hat back out a third time in 1983 to
investigate this propeller shape he
searched and searched but found nothing
there has since been much debate over
what Grim found whether the shape was in
fact a propeller or rather just a rock
with even his own scientists disputing
Grim over what the shape could be either
way it would never be located
again while Jack Grim was busy with his
Expeditions Robert Ballard had watched
from the sidelines disheartened by his
own failed attempt earlier but not ready
to fully give up on like Grim Ballard
did not have immense wealth at his
disposal but what he had was his own
unique Advantage ties with the US
Navy Ballard had approached the US Navy
with a proposal to design a new submers
that could be used to locate the Titanic
the Navy however wasn't so interested in
the Titanic but they were interested in
the
submersible the US Navy made Ballard a
deal they would fun his project but he
would need to use the equipment to help
them first on a completely different
Mission Ballard agreed and began to
develop this new tool for deep sea
exploration Argo Argo is a deep toad
sled that is remotely navigated above
the ocean floor attached to a research
vessel by a long cable and piloted by a
team on board the sled is outfitted with
Sid scanning sonar as well as cameras
that provide real real time Imaging of
the ocean
floor still in the late stages of the
Cold War the US Navy wanted to
investigate two nuclear submarines that
had been lost the USS fresher and the
USS scorpion however they didn't want
the Russians to know about this and so
Ballard was deployed in 1984 under the
guise of testing Argo in order to find
the Titanic in reality he was to map out
the wreckage side of both submarines in
order to assess any radioactive
[Music]
threats using Argo Ballard studied the
rec sites of the submarines and he began
to pick up on something peculiar about
both of them Ballard noticed that as the
warship sank to increasing deaths their
wreckages
imploded creating a debris field around
them the heavier pieces sank closer to
the wreckage itself but the lighter
pieces were carried away from the
wreckage leaving a sort of comet trail
around
it an idea began to form in Ballard's
mind while searching for the Titanic
everyone had attempted to find the ship
itself a needle in a Hy stack but what
if instead of trying to find the ship he
would look for the debris field that was
likely around the wreckage if he could
find any parts of the debris he could
follow the comet trail back to the ship
a revelation that would change
everything but before searching for the
Titanic Ballard would still need to bite
his time and continue his mission for
the US Navy he finally caught a lucky
break in 1985 when he was sent out once
again to map out the USS scorpion this
time however he would be allowed to use
any remaining time he had to take Argo
on a search for the
Titanic knowing the deadline would be
tied Ballard reached out to the French
oceanographic institution ifer and they
devised a two-face strategy the first
part of the search would be led by John
Lou Michelle of ifer and the second part
would be done by Robert Ballard the idea
was simple Michelle would first Scout
the entire search area using sonar
mapping just so that in the Second Step
Ballard could focus his limited time to
search only the most interesting spots
they came up with these two search areas
and while Robert Ballard was still
carrying out his mission for the Navy
Michelle would begin by using the same
moing the lawn technique that Jack Grim
had used scanning the ocean floor using
a more advanced sonar these search lines
were not always exactly straight ocean
currents would often drift the boat away
adding yet another challenge when it was
time for Balor to join and take over the
search Michelle had not found anything
and to add even more pressure to the
growing sense of another potential
failed Expedition only 12 days remained
before Ballard would need to return
whether he found anything or
not in order to use his limited time as
effective as possible Robert Ballard
came up with a plan informed by what he
has learned about the brief Fields he
would not look for the ship itself but
rather for its debris field he also knew
that on the night the Titanic sank there
was an ocean current going south
therefore lighter pieces in the debris
field should have drifted towards the
South he came up with an estimate of how
big the debris field should be now he
started searching but instead of
carefully doing lines over the entire
search area he would space out his Lines
Just far enough apart that he should
fear theoretically run into this debris
field spacing these lines out allows him
to cover a much larger area in a small
amount of time he also decided to rely
much more on the camera feedback rather
than on the sonar data cameras had been
used in past Expeditions such as when
Jack Grim believed he found a propeller
from the Titanic but his camera was not
capable of providing live video feed
Argo instead could and Ballard would be
almost exclusively relying on the video
rather than sonar his team would take
turns piloting Argo and watching the
video feed Around the Clock days rolled
by with nothing but the Landscapes of
the ocean floor passing through the
video feed and the crew was beginning to
feel the mounting pressure of the
approaching deadline the night watch was
especially difficult with the crew
making sure to keep themselves awake as
it felt like they watched the same
natural features Roll by minute for
minute but then suddenly the Rocks they
were watching started to look less like
rocks and more like man-made
debris now they were glued to the
screens the blurry images coming more
into
Focus definitely not
[Music]
rods not daring to look away for even a
second a crew member quickly flashed
pack down the ship's cook so that he
could grab Ballard from his room within
seconds Ballard joined the crew on their
monitors and after a few more tense
moments an even larger shape began to
fill the
screen there was no mistaking as they
had studied photos of the Titanic until
they knew every detail by heart Argo had
just passed over the Titanic
spoiler after 73 years of searching
they had finally found the
Titanic its location was a mere 3,300 ft
away from where Michelle had searched
previously the ocean currents drifting
him away from the
wreck immediate celebrations kicked off
disbelief and excitement making its way
through everyone on board but it was not
for long until the reality of what they
had found sank in and the celebration
was replaced with a moment of silence
with the crew honoring the more than
1,500 people who perished during this
tragedy the boiler the team had found
was not far off from even more debris
and the team soon found the stern
section of the
ship when it sank the ship violently
broke into two parts and about 800 y
from the stern they then also discovered
the bow with the now iconic railing
still
intact and now that the ship was found
it did not take long until people wanted
to recover it a dream that had long been
imagined and even inspired a Hollywood
film years prior and smaller artifacts
were soon brought up but one man had
larger
Ambitions not far off from where the
original boiler was discovered there is
a large section of the ship's Hall that
could be
recovered on August 27 1996 everything
was
prepared free Expedition ships were
circling the site and right next to them
are two large cruise ships the recovery
mission was to be a media spectacle with
thousands of guests including Titanic
survivors and even celebrities on board
using a submersible special bags were
attached to the piece and soon it starts
to rise from the ocean floor with cheers
all throughout the cruise ships but then
things start going wrong good evening
everyone I'm Brad Edwards here in the
forecast center of the weather channel
of course special coverage continues
with hurricane eduard which is posing a
threat to the Eastern
Coastline the full story of the raising
of the Titanic is fascinating and it is
one of many twists and turns which is
why I have produced a fulllength video
about this Mission explaining exactly
how the piece was supposed to be raised
what went wrong and what this story
tells us about whether we should recover
artifacts in the first
place this video was part of my ongoing
series under exposure in which I create
my most ambitious larger budget
documentaries I've also made a video
about the tenor disaster the worst
aviation accident that ever happened as
well as a video about the US military
raate on the bin Laden
compound these are the videos that I am
most proud of making they are
documentaries that are not made for the
YouTube algorithm but unrushed cinematic
storytelling this series is exclusive to
nebula a streaming site that I'm
building together with other creators
where we can create these higher budget
Originals so go to
[Music]